An Inventory to the Pardee Lowe papers, 1911-1995
Hoover Institution Archives
- International House Peace Meeting notes, 1936 April 21 (Box 387)
- Clippings, 1972-1973 (Box 387)
- Department of State Education Officer files related to UNESCO, 1960s-1970s (Box 388)
- Association for Asian Studies conference notes, 1973 March (Box 388)
- Secondary education clippings, 1920s-1970s. (Box 388)
  Includes clippings related to a solo exhibition by then-ten-year-old Wah Ming Chang, 1928 July. Also includes Mrs. Pardee Lowe, students' recital program, Chinese YWCA, San Francisco, 1935 April
- Clippings, 1930s and 1970s (Box 388)
- Chinatown and Chinese Americans research files, 1920s-1970s. (Box 389-391.)
- Writing drafts and correspondence related to Lowe's San Francisco Chinatown study for LaPiere and for the IPR, 1930s (Box 389-391.)
- "A Project for the Completion of 'A Sociological Study of San Francisco's Chinatown' (As Part of the Research Program of the American Council, I.P.R.),", 1936 April 23 (Box 389-391.)
- IPR project sponsors correspondence, 1936 (Box 389-391.)
- "'Cost of Living' Survey of Chinese Wage Earners in San Francisco - Study made by Juvenile Court with Cooperation of Heller Committee for Research in Social Economics From January 1, 1933 to December 31, 1933," data forms (Box 389-391.)
- Chinatowns and Chinese Americans research files, 1920s-1970s. (Box 389)
  Includes draft writings, notes, correspondence, ephemeral printed materials, and newspaper clippings, in English and in Chinese
- Stanford University coursework notes (Box 389)
- Clippings relate to discrimination against Chinese Americans, Japanese Americans, and African Americans, 1920s-1970s (Box 389)
- "Chinatown Sees Red," writing draft, undated, probably 1930s (Box 389)
- "Chinatown First National Bank" typescript notes related to planning for a bank in San Francisco, 1955 August (Box 389)
- Notes and clippings related to economics and business (Box 389)
- "Statement of Present JACL Objectives," Japanese American Citizens League, Washington, DC, undated, with notes (Box 389)
- Printed materials (Box 389)
  - Chinese Directory of San Francisco and East Bay the Chinese Commercial Bureau in Cooperation with the Chinese Consolidated Benevolent Association of San Francisco, 1949 (Box 389)
  - Membership Index: Chinese Chamber of Commerce San Francisco, printed by Zhong Xi Ri Bao (Chung Sai Yat Po, Chinese-West Daily), 1930 (Box 389)
  - Chinese Telephone Directory, San Francisco Pacific Telephone and Telegraph Company, 1933 March (Box 389)
  - Clippings and subject file material, 1970s (Box 389)
- "Outline of Possible Subjects for Rotogravure Treatment in San Francisco's Chinatown," typescript, likely prepared for consideration of the San Francisco Chronicle, 1938 July 17 (Box 391)
- IPR project sponsors correspondence, 1936 (Box 391)
- Clippings, 1987 (Box 392)
- Free China cause printed materials, 1960s-1980s (Box 393-396.)
- Clippings and public bulletins of the State Department and the Institute of Current World Affairs, 1987 (Box 393-396.)
- 1943 book galleys (Box 393-396.)
- Unopened mail (Box 395)
- "Tanzania Fact Wallet," Tanzania Information Services, Dar Es Salaam, undated (Box 395)
- Printed material, 1960s-1970 (Box 396)
- Golden Gate International Exhibition (GGIE) Pacific House planning files, 1938 (Box 397-407.)
  - Typescript notes of directions from Philip N. Youtz and concepts behind and details of interpretative work to be executed by painter Miguel Covarrubias (Box 397-401.)
- Soviet Union reports on relations between the U.S. and U.S.S.R., 1950s (Box 397)
- USIS work printed material, 1950s-1980s (bulk 1960s-1970s) (Box 397-401.)
- Free China cause printed material, 1950s-1980s (bulk 1960s-1970s) (Box 397-401.)
- International Cooperation Administration publications (Box 397-401.)
- Mutual Security Mission to China, Taipei, Taiwan (Box 401)
- United States Educational Foundation in China documents, 1947-1964 (Box 402)
- U.S. Military Assistance Advisory Group to the Republic of China (MAAG), Taipei, Taiwan, telephone directory, classifieds, and guide, 1965 September (Box 405)
- State Department memos of wide circulation, 1960s-1970s (Box 405)
- UNESCO and the UN clippings, 1970s-1980s (Box 405)
- Reports related to USAID, 1960s-1970s (Box 406)
- Chinatown study files, 1930s (Box 408)
- Typescript index cards notes from library research, likely in support of GGIE, undated (Box 408)
- Index cards with detailed information about residents of San Francisco Chinatown, arranged by street, 1932 and 1934 (bulk 1934). (Box 408)
  Often includes information about subject's relatives and profession or pay
- CIA, illustrated atlas of China, 1971 (Box 409)
- Oversize rolled documents (Box 409)
- Printed materials related to Lowe's UNESCO work, 1957-1990s (bulk 1960s-1970s) (Box 410-433)
  - Emergency Management of the National Economy, Correspondence Study Branch of the Industrial College of the Armed Forces, 1950 (Box 411)
  - Africa Report, 1963-1972 (Box 414)
  - "Theater in Mexico" special issue, Theatre Arts Monthly, Miguel Covarrubias, special editor, 1938 August (Box 427)
  - Index of Research Projects Volume 1, Works Progress Administration (WPA), 1938 (Box 428)
  - The Word in the World '67: Divine Word Missionaries Report on Their Part in Bringing the Word of God to the Whole World, Divine Word Missionaries special issue on China, Techny, Illinois, 1967 (Box 433)
- U.S. Air Force training materials, 1950s-1960 (Box 434)
  - Extension Course Institute, U.S. Air Force, Course 7200, Information Services Officer, Volumes 1-2 Part A, 1958 (Box 434)
  - Volume 3 Community Relations part B Examination booklet, 1957 March. (Box 434)
    Holographic notation "completed and mailed Dec 31, 1960"
  - U.S. Air Force, Intelligence Fundamentals Course of the Continental Air Command Specialized Training Program, "CONAC Specialized Training Manual, No. 45-2000," Volume III, 1956; Volume V, 1957 (Box 434)
  - Department of the Air Force, "Security: Safeguarding Military Information," Air Force Regulation No. 205-1, 1956 January 3 (Box 434)
- Industrial College of the Armed Forces, Washington, DC, training materials, 1953-1955 (Box 434)
- Counterintelligence Corps Advanced Training School notes, 28th Enlisted Class, 1943 October - November (Box 435)
  - "Chinese or Chinese-Speaking Agents 28th Enlisted Men's School of the Advanced CIC, Chicago, Illinois," typescript list by Pardee Lowe, undated, probably 1943 (Box 435)
- Biographical file, 1929-1944. (Box 435)
  Includes Lowe's drivers licenses, selective service registration certificate, and immunization register
- U.S. Army training materials and course notes, 1943 (Box 435)
  Includes materials for training at the Engineer School, Fort Belvoir, Virginia, the Military Intelligence Training Center, and the Counterintelligence Corps Detachment, Intelligence Division, Third Service Command, Baltimore, Maryland
- Field Economic Mobilization Course training materials and notes, 1951-1953. (Box 435)
  Consists of documents related to training conducted by the San Francisco Chamber of Commerce in cooperation with the Twelfth Naval District, Fourth Air Force, and Sixth Army, 1953 February 9-20. Includes roster of conferees, 1953, and correspondence regarding enrolling, 1952-1953
- Clippings related to national defense, economy, natural resources, and Korea, 1953 (Box 435)
- "A Soviet Air Mission - 1944 as Described by a Soviet Air Force Defector 1948," U.S. Air Force Reserves, undated (Box 435)
- "Soviet Slang," U.S. Air Force Reserves, undated (Box 435)
- Industrial College of the Armed Forces, Field Economic Mobilization Course materials, 1952-1953 (Box 435)
  - Clippings, 1953 (Box 435)
  - Industrial College of the Armed Forces (Box 435)
  - "Field Economic Mobilization Course, lecture outlines, San Francisco, California, 9-20 February 1953." Includes notes (Box 435)
  - "Economic Mobilization," 1952 September 1 (Box 435)
  - "Emergency Management of the National Economy, Correspondence Study Course," 1951-1952 (Box 435)
- Examinations on volumes I through IV correspondence, 1952 (Box 435)
- USAF training materials, 1950s-1960 (Box 435)
  - Extension Course Institute, U.S. Air Force, Course 7200, Information Services Officer, volume 2 part B - volume 3, 1958 (Box 435)
- CIC training and administrative files, 1941-1946. (Box 436)
  Includes correspondence, 1941-1946, mainly recommendation letters and other correspondence regarding administrative matters
- Correspondence related to Lowe's 1943 books (Box 436)
  - Typescript correspondence log relative to joining army and seeking army career with active service in field intelligence and operations in Asia, particularly with the Office of Strategic Services (OSS), 1941-1944, undated (Box 436)
  - Resumes, 1945 (Box 436)
  - Other administrative documents, including related to service in China-Burma-India Theater, 1945-1946 (Box 436)
  - Honorable discharge documents, 1945-1946 (Box 436)
  - Typescript report regarding assignment to interview Newark, New Jersey, public librarian John Boynton Kaiser regarding the Negro Community of that area, 1943 June 15 (Box 436)
- Lowe's World War II service diaries, 1942-1945 (Box 436)
- Photographs, "received NYC 5/8/46," including Stanford campus and Lowe, undated (Box 436)
- Clippings, mainly related to the CIC, CIA, and FBI, 1942-1974 (Box 436)
- China, Communism, and the Free China cause reports and pamphlets, 1926-1964. (Box 437-443.)
  Consists mainly of published reports by the U.S. government, the Department of State Office of Intelligence Research, Massachusetts Institute of Technology, and others, compiled and bound, likely in the 1960s
- Free China pamphlets and ephemeral propaganda publications (Box 439)
- Communist China propaganda publications (Box 439)
- IPR published research reports, some labeled as part of the 1936 Yosemite Conference readings (Box 439-440.)
- Lottery files, 1930s-1950s (Box 441-442.)
  1990s
  - "Notes on Chinese Lottery," typescript, 1938 July 30 (Box 441-442.)
    Includes rules for Chinese and "American" lotteries, accompanied by data on lottery drawing numbers for Fook Chun "Fu Chun" Chinese lottery and "American" lottery, 1938
  - Lottery tickets, mainly organized by date, 1949-1950 and 1995 (Box 441-442.)
  - Casino brochures on Keno, including a history of development of Chinese lottery into Keno in Nevada (Box 441-442.)
- USSR related reports (Box 442-443.)
- Draft writings, 1940s (Box 443)
  - Writing by others, 1948-1949 (Box 443)
    - Yao, Shelia, "China Nurse," typescript, 1948 (Box 443)
      Includes correspondence between Lowe and potential publisher, 1948-1949
  - Lowe, Pardee, "Chinese Marco Polo," typescript, undated, likely 1940s. (Box 443)
    Draft of novel about young man who leaves China for the "land of the Golden Mountains" emigrating to the U.S. for opportunity
- Writing files, 1930s-1970s (bulk 1930s-1940s) (Box 444)
- Manuscripts, 1939-1940, undated (Box 444)
- "The Return of the 'Natives,'" typescript, undated (Box 444)
  Related to return of native-born U.S. citizens of Chinese descent returning to U.S. from China due to the Sino-Japanese conflict
- Writings by others (Box 444)
- Clippings from The Saturday Evening Post, 1939-1940, undated (Box 444)
- Speeches typescripts, 1939, undated (Box 444)
- Chinese Counsel General, San Francisco, including for GGIE Jade Pagoda Preview, 1939 August 8. (Box 444)
  See also box 326
- Draft of constitution and bylaws for a new organization, possibly to be named the China Society of the Pacific Coast, undated (Box 444)
- Gloria Ting speech, Tokyo International Church, 1978 January 31 (Box 444)
- "Personalities" writing materials file, 1930s-1970. (Box 444)
  Consists mainly of clippings and USIS news releases related to Chinese Americans in San Francisco, California, and the U.S.
- Sino-Japanese War and China Emergency Relief Committee subject files, 1920s-1960s (Box 444)
- Typescript notes, 1937, undated (Box 444)
- Holographic notes, likely 1950s (Box 444)
- Printed materials related to building support for and raising funds for China relief (Box 444)
- The Chinatown Monthly Volume 1 Number 2, San Francisco: Chinatown Amateur Students' Association (Box 444)
- Typescript copies of letters by unidentified writer, possibly K. C. Li, 1932 January - March (Box 444)
- Accounts of Communist China as seen by foreign visitors, typescript, 1949, undated (Box 444)
- Clippings (Box 444)
- USIS job applications and tuberculosis records related to Lowe's post in Taiwan, 1960 (Box 444)
- Documents related to Pong Sing, San Diego Toggery, 1920s-1930s. (Box 444)
  Includes bank account books, business ledger, correspondence, and company reports. Most documents in Chinese
- Chinese Exclusion Act immigration documents related to Oakland, California merchant Pon Sing, member of L. So and Co., Oakland, 1911 (Box 444)
- Writing files, 1935-1940, undated (bulk 1938-1939) (Box 444)
  - IPR survey of San Francisco Chinatown draft writings (Box 445)
  - San Francisco Chronicle's This World Magazine articles related to the Sino-Japanese war and international politics, 1938 (Box 445)
  - "The Rape of Nanking," by George A. Fitch, as told to Pardee Lowe, published in This World, 1938 June 12, and correspondence with Fitch, YMCA secretary returned from China (Box 445)
  - Correspondence with publishers (Box 445)
- Writings by others, including clippings from Saturday Evening Post, Collier's, The Rotarian, 1938-1939 (Box 445)
- Dr. Hu Shih subject file, 1930s-1960s (bulk 1960s) (Box 446)
- Harvard Business School case studies of Tatung Co., Taiwan, 1981 March 18 and 1984 November 6 (Box 446)
- Air Force Intelligence Fundamentals printed materials and course notes, 1953-1958 (Box 446)
- Air Force Intelligence Fundamentals printed materials and course notes, 1953-1958 (Box 447)
- "Speech for General Wedemeyer, at Dedication of Memorial Plaque in St. Mary's Park [San Francisco Chinatown], May 30, 1951," with printed program (Box 447)
- Correspondence and clippings related to speeches by Lowe 1946-1954, including at the Commonwealth Club, 1946 and 1950 (Box 447)
- Sueling Li, of Sueling, Inc., New York correspondence, 1962 (Box 447)
- "Prospectus on Taiwan," Sueling Li, 1961 September 12 (Box 447)
- USIA post administrative files, 1955-1972 (Box 447)
  - Descriptions of geographic areas and international organizations monitored, 1971 (Box 447)
  - Self-evaluation reports by Lowe, including reports on growth of the Fulbright program in Taiwan, the establishment of the Stanford Center of Chinese Studies in Taipei, and the Foo Hsing Opera (Fu Hsing Opera) (Box 447)
  - Evaluations of Lowe and personnel documents related to other staff (Box 447)
  - "USIS-Taipei Cultural Affairs Section," organizational chart, undated, which includes relations of Cultural Affairs Officer, ICA (International Communication Agency), USEF in China, and private foundations (Box 447)
- Biographical file, 1940s-1993 (Box 448)
  - Correspondence, applications, and curriculum vitae related to seeking employment, 1946-1955. (Box 448)
  - Results of Lowe's assignment to rewrite his job description to more accurately reflect activities, 1963 (Box 448)
  - List of major duties, 1970 October 12 (Box 448)
  - "Statement of Personal History (Forwarded to Director, Armed Forces Security Agency, Washington 25, D. C.),", 1951 June 19 (Box 448)
  - Evaluations of Lowe by J. A. B. and R. M. M., 1961 March 30 (Box 448)
- Biographical file, 1940s-1993 (Box 448)
  - Hiring letters, letters of commendation, and clippings related to career, 1949-1973 (Box 448)
  - USIS Reunion photos, Los Angeles, 1993 March 27 (Box 448)
  - Self-evaluation reports by Lowe, annual performance report regarding other staff, curriculum vitae, and documents related to the training of Lowe's successor (Box 448)
  - Letter to Marshal Lowe concerning family shares in the Bank of Canton, 1965 January 21 (Box 448)
- Department of State Education Officer files, Consultancies, 1969-1970s (Box 448)
- Correspondence mainly related to distribution or exchanges of printed materials, 1970s (Box 448)
- Correspondence related to applicants desiring to register as educational consultants, 1970s (Box 448)
- Department of State bulletins and related clippings, 1970s-1990s (Box 449)
- USIA alumni directories, newsletters, and clippings, 1980s-1990s (Box 449)
- IPR administrative files, 1936-1937 January (Box 449)
  - Yosemite conference planning administrative correspondence, including list of books. Some material in Chinese (Box 449)
  - "Chinese in California" project stipends (Box 449)
- "Pardee Lowe and IPR Appointment," undated, probably 1936. (Box 449)
  Consists of extracts of correspondence among IPR leaders regarding candidate search for employee with Japanese or Chinese language ability
- "W. L. Holland's Movements during 1936-1937,", 1936 May 9 (Box 449)
- Stanford Alumni Association files, 1947-1949 (Box 449)
- Father and Glorious Descendant reprint correspondence, 1950s-1970s (bulk 1960s-1970s). (Box 449)
  Includes typescript copies of excepts and clippings related to publishing, copyright, and authors
- Correspondence regarding employment, work history, and biographical information, 1925-1930s (Box 449)
- Public speaking appearance correspondence and clippings, 1933-1935 (Box 449)
- Clippings related to U.S. Air Force, 1950s and 1973 (Box 450)
- Counterintelligence Corps continuation and re-application correspondence, 1946-1950s (Box 450)
- Army service induction files and application files, 1941-1943. (Box 450)
  Includes clippings, 1940s and 1970s (bulk 1940s)
- Correspondence, 1942-1944. (Box 450)
  Includes clippings, 1950s and 1970s
- Air Force service administrative files, 1952 (Box 450)
- Correspondence, 1944-1945. (Box 450)
  In English and Chinese
  - Sun Fo, Legislative Yuan, Chungking, China, and other correspondence among New Delhi, Chungking, and other service locations (Box 450)
  - "Madame's speech," 1944 July 5, typescript, addressing the allegations of infidelity by her husband, Chiang Kai-shek (Box 450)
- Air Force Reserve administrative files, 1952-1970. (Box 450)
  Includes applications for active duty counterintelligence and psychological warfare training
- Clippings, 1972-1973 (Box 450)
- USEF administrative files, employment applications and correspondence, 1946-1965 (bulk 1940s) (Box 450)
- Father and Glorious Descendant reprint correspondence, 1965 (Box 450)
  1970s
- Asian Wall Street Journal, letter to editor, 1983 June 17 (Box 450)
  In which Lowe responds to the review of his 1943 book by Professor Elaine Kim
- Father and Glorious Descendant reprint correspondence, 1982-1996. (Box 450)
  Includes copies of checks and dust jacket from third printing, 1943
- "Father's Robes of Immortality," typescript drafts of 1937, and correspondence with publishers, 1937-1940 (Box 451)
- Clippings and correspondence related to seeking role in production of film version of Pearl Buck's China Sky, 1940-1942 (Box 451)
- "Year of Momentous Decision," typescript, PhD coursework, with cover letter to advisor Professor Lantzeff, 1952 September 9 (Box 451)
- U.S. Air Force Reserve personnel files, 1951-1964 (Box 451)
- Army service records and personnel files, 1945-1960s. (Box 451)
  Includes photo, probably 1940s, and clippings related to the military and veterans affairs, 1960s-1980s. See also boxes 466 and 468
- Writings, 1930s-1955 (Box 452)
  - "Jo Ho See: Deeds to Match American Aspirations for Victory," typescript, 1943 January 30 (Box 452)
  - Father and Glorious Descendant, typescript drafts, including first draft 1942, and third draft, 1942 July 8 (Box 452)
  - Correspondence, 1937-1955. (Box 452)
    Mainly related to publishing Lowe's writings
  - "Chinatown Still Goes Forth to War," typescript draft, undated, probably 1930s (Box 452)
  - Father and Glorious Descendant, list of reviews to date, 1943 April 22 (Box 452)
- Clippings, 1960s (Box 452)
  - American Negro subject file, 1960s. (Box 452)
    Consists mainly of clippings, mostly related to current events, especially civil rights, and to education
  - Race prejudice clippings file, 1920s-1960s. (Box 452)
    Includes clippings related to immigration reform
- U.S. history class notes, 1926 (Box 452)
- Account book, 1930-1932 (Box 452)
  Listing holdings, mainly of members of Liu (Lowe) clan, in Chinese, hand-bound
- Clippings, 1930s-1960s (Box 453)
- Correspondence, 1940s-1980s (Box 454)
- Raymond L. Tweedy, founder of Chinese Management Association, Nanking, correspondence, 1940s-1980s. (Box 454)
  See also box 459
- Foreign Service subject file, 1940s-1960s (Box 454)
- USIS bilingual publications, Taipei, Taiwan, 1964, undated, 1962 or later (Box 454)
- Clippings, 1920s-1960s (Box 454)
- Correspondence, 1930s-1990s (Box 455)
  - Denman, Mrs. Leslie, 1940s-1960s. (Box 455)
    Includes correspondence with Judge William Denman and others
  - Foo Hsing Drama (Fu Hsing Opera) appearances clippings and correspondence, 1950s-1970s. (Box 455)
    Includes Office of the Psychological Warfare Officer, United States Army Japan, research analysis: "China: The All-China Federation of Trade Unions (ACFTU)," 1957 October 9
  - Dandison, Basil G., 1960s-1990s (Box 455)
  - Davies, John H. and others, 1930s-1980 (Box 455)
  - Sisters of the Order of Saint Benedict, 1960s-1995. (Box 455)
    Includes records of donations
  - Alsberg, Dr. Carl, Emma Alsberg and others, 1940s (Box 455)
  - Tunghai University, Taiwan, and United Board for Christian Higher Education in Asia, 1960s-1970s. (Box 455)
- Correspondence, 1950s-1960s (Box 455)
- Correspondence, 1930-1990 (Box 456)
  - Ruiz, Antonio M. ("Corcito"), 1939-1941. (Box 456)
    Includes printed material
  - Mei Ya Publications, Inc., 1960s-1970s. (Box 456)
    Includes correspondence by others, and clippings, 1980s
  - Riles, Wilson, 1970s. (Box 456)
    Includes clippings, 1970s-1982; correspondence with others, 1948-1970s; and directory of Rotary Club of Nanking, 1948
  - Fu Jen University, 1960s-1990. (Box 456)
    Includes records of donations to Fu Jen University and Divine Word Missionaries
  - International House of Berkeley, California, and New York, 1930s-1990s. (Box 456)
    Includes minutes of alumni association meetings, correspondence, and printed materials
  - Liu, Wellington, 1930-1940s. (Box 456)
    Includes correspondence by others, and clippings, 1960s-1980s
- Correspondence, 1940s-1960s (Box 457)
  - Wilbur, Ray Lyman, 1940s. (Box 457)
    Includes correspondence with Leonard Wilbur and others
  - Won, Virgil, 1940s-1960s (Box 457)
- China United Products Co., Shanghai, Lowe's correspondence as sales manager, 1946-1947 (Box 457)
- Schering Company correspondence, clippings, and printed materials, 1945-1947 (Box 457)
- Correspondence related to seeking employment, 1935-1939 (Box 457)
- Wah Chang Trading Corporation, 1940s. (Box 457)
  Mainly documents related to applicants for office work. Includes personal information and in-house assessments of candidates
- Schering Company files, 1946-1947. (Box 457)
  Includes sales training notes, correspondence, and blueprint of 55 Si Kong Road, Nanking, as occupied
- Personal correspondence, 1946-1947 (Box 457)
- Rusk, Dean, and Mrs. Dean Rusk correspondence, 1950-1995 (Box 457)
- China House Association files, 1954-1957 (Box 458)
- U.S. Air Force Reserves and Industrial College of the Armed Forces training course materials, 1950s-1960s. (Box 458)
  Includes Information Services Officer student progress chart
- IPR conference files, 1936 (Box 458)
  Related to 1936 Yosemite Conference and to "Informal Weekend Conference held at Sunset Farm, Lee, Mass., May 31st and June 1st,1936"
- Appointment book, 1965 (Box 458)
- Clippings, largely related to politics and education, 1950s-1960 (Box 458)